# Chirag Gupta, Ph.D.

Postdoctoral Associate, Computational Biology University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin, Madison, 53705, USA Webpage: cngupta.github.io

Email: chiraggupta.bioinfo@gmail.com

Phone: (479) 799-7136

# SUMMARY

Bioinformatics Scientist with 8+ years of experience in data-driven scientific investigations of human and plant systems. My objective is to develop bioinformatics solutions for integrating multi-omics data and applications of advanced machine learning techniques to guide clinical decision making and design efficacious wet lab experiments. I have extensive experience in written and oral communication to academics and business leaders through contributions to winning grants, 10+ peer reviewed publications, 4+ oral and 10+ poster presentations.

# **EDUCATION**

2017	Ph.D. Cell and Molecular Biology (Computational) Dissertation: Transcriptome-based gene networks for systems-level analysis of gene function in plants	University of Arkansas, Fayetteville
2009	M.Sc. Bioinformatics	Sardar Patel University, India
2007	B.Sc. Bioinformatics	Sardar Patel University, India
		•

# RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE			
2021 - present	Postdoctoral Research Associate	University of Wisconsin,	
·	<ul> <li>Neuropsychiatric disorders</li> </ul>	Madison, Wisconsin, USA	
	Single cell gene regulatory networks		
	Heterogenous data integration		
2017 – 2020	Postdoctoral Research Associate	University of Arkansas,	
2017 2020	Rice environmental stress biology	Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA	
	<b>5</b> ,	r dyetteville, Atkarisas, con	
	Network-based machine learning for  and prioritization		
	gene prioritization		
	<ul> <li>Web applications (GRAiN)</li> </ul>		
2012 – 2017	Graduate Research Assistant	University of Arkansas,	
	<ul> <li>Plant stress and developmental biology</li> </ul>	Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA	
	<ul> <li>Transcriptomics</li> </ul>		
	<ul> <li>Gene coexpression networks</li> </ul>		
	<ul> <li>Web applications (RECoN, SANe)</li> </ul>		
2008 — 2009	Student Researcher	Disha Life Sciences Pvt. Ltd.,	
	<ul> <li>Fusion proteins in cancer</li> </ul>	Gujarat, India	
	Protein structure prediction	,,	
	<ul> <li>Molecular modeling, drug designing</li> </ul>		
	• Molecular modeling, drug designing		

### **PUBLICATIONS**

# Under review/preprints

1. **Chirag Gupta**, Arjun Krishnan, Andrew Schneider, Cynthia Denbow, Eva Collakova, Pawel Wolinski, Andy Pereira. SANe: The Seed Active Network for Discovering Transcriptional Regulatory Programs of Seed Development. bioRxiv, doi: 10.1101/165894 (in revision)

### *In preparation*

- 1. Applications of artificial intelligence and machine learning to multimodal data in intellectual and developmental disabilities (*review*; 2022)
- 2. Network analysis of primary and secondary cell types of the human brain. (in preparation)

# Peer reviewed journal articles

- 1. **Chirag Gupta**, Venkategowda Ramegowda, Supratim Basu, Andy Pereira. Using network-based machine learning to predict transcription factors involved in drought stress resistance. (accepted, Front. in genetics, 2021)
- 2. Raksha Singh, Rohana Liyanage, **Chirag Gupta**, Jackson Lay Jr., Andy Pereira, Clemencia Rojas. The protein interactomes of AtNHR2A and AtNHR2B unraveled common and specialized functions in plant immunity integrating distinct biological processes. *Frontiers in Plant Science*, *March 2020. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2020.00232*.
- 3. Min Woo Lee, Carmen S. Padilla, **Chirag Gupta**, Aravind Galla, Andy Pereira, Jiamei Li, Fiona L. Goggin. The FATTY ACID DESATURASE 2 family in tomato contributes to primary metabolism and stress responses. *Plant Physiology*, *Nov. 2019. doi:10.1104/pp.19.00487*.
- Chirag Gupta and Andy Pereira. Recent advances in gene function prediction using context-specific coexpression networks in plants. F1000Research, Feb. 2019. doi: 10.12688/f1000research.17207.1.
- 5. Arjun Krishnan, **Chirag Gupta**, Madana MR Ambavaram, Andy Pereira. RECoN: Rice Environment Co-expression Network for systems level analysis of abiotic-stress response. *Frontiers in Plant Science*, Sep. 2017. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2017.01640
- 6. Venkategowda Ramegowda, Upinder Singh Gill, Palaiyur Nanjappan Sivalingam, Aarti Gupta, **Chirag Gupta**, Geetha Govind, Karaba N Nataraja, Andy Pereira, Makarla Udayakumar, Kirankumar S Mysore, Muthappa Senthil-Kumar. GBF3 transcription factor imparts drought tolerance in Arabidopsis thaliana. *Scientific Reports*, *August 2017. doi:* 10.1038/s41598-017-09542-1.
- 7. Venkategowda Ramegowda, Supratim Basu, **Chirag Gupta**, Andy Pereira. Regulation of grain yield in rice under well-watered and drought stress conditions by GUDK. *Plant Signaling and Behavior*, *January 2015. doi: 10.1080/15592324.2015.1034421*.

### Published project reports

1. Anuj Kumar, Sara Yingling, Julie Thomas, Charles Ruiz, Yheni Dwiningsih, **Chirag Gupta**, Paul Counce, T.J. Siebenmorgen, Karen A.K. Moldenhauer, Andy Pereira. Screening of Indica and Japonica rice subspecies for grain yield and quality under high nighttime temperature. *B.R. Wells Arkansas Rice Research Studies* 2018, 659:61-66.

2. Ramegowda Venkategowda, Subodh Srivastava, Julie Thomas, **Chirag Gupta**, Supratim Basu, Paul Counce, Ya-Jane Wang, Terry Siebenmorgen, Karen Moldenhauer, Andy Pereira. Genetic basis of altered grain quality in different rice cultivars under high nighttime temperature. *B.R. Wells Arkansas Rice Research Studies* 2015, 634:79-85.

# Conference Presentations

#### Talks

- Predicting rice genes important for drought tolerance using gene regulatory networks and machine learning. Crops InSilico, 4th Annual Symposium and Hackathon, Urbana, IL, 3rd May 2019
- Arabidopsis seed-filling association-network analysis. American Society of Plant Biologists – Southern Section (ASPB-SS), Lexington, KY, 30th March 2014.

### Select posters

- Network-based approach to prioritize lung cancer genes from whole-exome sequencing data. AR-BIC, Little Rock, AR, 25th March 2018
- Differential Co-expression: A new paradigm for identification of candidate genes from expression data. AR-BIC, Little Rock, AR, 24th April 2017
- An abiotic-stress conditioned gene regulatory network in rice predicted using an ensemble of reverse-engineering solutions. The 25th Plant and Animal Genome (PAG) Conference, San Diego, CA, 14th January 2017
- A resource for systems analysis of stress response in rice. NSF Workshop on plant development and drought stress, Monterey, CA, 8th November 2015
- StarchNet: Implications of high night-time temperature on starch metabolism regulatory networks in rice. AR NSF EPSCoR Annual Meeting, Fayetteville, AR, 15th September 2015
- In Silico Analysis of Fusion Proteins in Cancer, International Conference on Biomedical and Genomic Research, Ahmedabad, India, 30th January 2009

### AWARDS

- Crops in silico underrepresented minority travel scholarship, Crops InSilico, Urbana, IL, 2019
- 2. Scherago International Student Travel Grants Awards, **The 25th annual Plant and Animal Genome (PAG) meeting**, San Diego, CA, 2017
- 3. NSF Travel Grant to attend the Workshop on Plant Development and Drought Stress, **National Science Foundation**, 2015
- 4. Stood 3rd in merit list for all India entrance examination for Master's in bioinformatics program, **Sardar Patel University**, India, 2007
- 5. 2nd Prize in undergraduate oral presentation, Sardar Patel University, India, 2006
- 6. 3rd Prize in undergraduate poster competition, Atmiya University, India, 2006

# **GRANT CONTRIBUTIONS**

- NSF EPSCoR RII Track-2 FEC 1826836: Systems genetics studies on rice genomes for analysis of grain yield and quality under heat stress (PI: Dr. Andy Pereira; \$4,659,406), 2018
- **NSF MCB 1716844**: Systems genetics analysis of photosynthetic carbon metabolism in rice (PI: Dr. Andy Pereira; \$798,725.00), 2017

# SOCIETY MEMBERSHIPS

2019 - present The International Society for Computational Biology (ISCB)

SELECT SKILLS

**Programming** R, Perl, PHP, mySQL

**Bioinformatics** Docker, STAR, Tuxedo suite, BWA, Samtools, GATK, Picard, VarScan,

Mutect, SomaticSniper, VCFtools, edgeR, DESeq, limma, LibSVM, Weka,

BLAST, Arguslab, MolSoft, Rasmol, I-TASSER etc.

Visualization R, CytoscapeWeb, D3.js

Platforms UNIX, Linux, Google cloud, MacOS

Version control Github

# TOOLS DEVELOPED

**GRAINS** http://rrn.uark.edu/shiny/apps/rrn/

**SANe** https://plantstress-pereira.uark.edu/SANe/ https://plantstress-pereira.uark.edu/RECoN/

# TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Co-taught Plant Genomics (**Bioinformatics/Genomics modules**: CSES 5543, Uni. Of Arkansas), 2016, 2018

# **EXTENSION ACTIVITIES**

Student and Teacher Workshop: rice genetic variation (18 credit hours, Uni. Of Arkansas), 2019

# ACADEMIC SERVICE

- **Manuscript reviewer** for Plant Physiology, Frontiers in Plant Science, Nature Scientific Reports, Rice, Plant Cell Reports, Horticultural Plant Journal, Plant Methods
- Plante Fellow 2019: Contribution to the Plantae online portal for Bioinformatics resources relevant to plant biology research
- Member of the panel of judges for the Northwest Arkansas Regional Science and Engineering Fair 2015,16
- Conducted several training material and hands-on activities for undergraduates and K-12 students from the Arkansas agricultural areas in the Delta region for a STEM literacy outreach program

# REFREES

Available upon request